welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
so me and maria clara we co-founded uh
together the project uh called this is
not the truth
it's a project based on
youtube channel mainly we created
content we did a web series i think some
of you
uh watched it the commentary series
called what what is emerging
and we released that a year ago
and apart from that series we've been
doing um
some other interviews that are on the
web channel and we have a channel on
instagram as well
the idea with this project this is not
the truth is to
investigate emerging narratives for
paradigm shift
so we were on a quest when we first met
at schumacher college in the uk apart
from the fact that we are brazilian we
are not from the same city in brazil
so we met when we were in england and we
started this project a couple of years
ago
and that has been one of our main
occupations
until now but tonight we were here
actually to talk about other projects
that i
that i take part is the collective
gesturing towards the colonial futures
that it's called gtdf collective i'll
put the link here afterwards
and this is also related to the research
that i do together with maria clara but
it's not always translated into like
video content as we do with this is not
the truth it's usually more
research in the field we work a lot with
indigenous people
and mainly we work with pedagogical
experiments
on how we can move out of the frames of
modernity that we are sort of
stuck in so that's a brief introduction
maria let's see if we can hear you
sorry everyone is that i'm in the
countryside so the internet is totally
weird
so sorry for that i see that camille
already
talked briefly about the gesturing
towards the colonial future
collective so my question would be
what is gesturing towards the colonial
futures
collective
so yeah i was just talking like the
structure of the collective i'll tell a
little bit about the
the story right it's actually really
connected to canada
because it was started by a professor
that is now
that has been teaching in ubc in
vancouver
for quite a while now and this teacher
is vanessa andreochi
and she's brazilian but she has been
living in canada for a while
and she has a chair in race inequality
and global education
at ubc so she started she started the
gesturing towards the colonial futures
as a space where we could do
experimental pedagogical research
on how we could move away from the
colonial forms of being and living that
we are usually trapped in
and every time we try to do something
different we try to like
fix something or go more sustainable or
be more just
or inclusive and things like that that
i'm sure
quite a few here are familiar with those
movements
a lot of times we feel ourselves trapped
in the same kind of paradigm and
repeating the same kind of mistakes even
though we have a different intention
so so we've been doing pedagogical
experiments
the collective exists for five years
more or less
i've joined for uh two years now
so it's there's this connection directly
to canada because
of professor vanessa andreyochi and also
with some of the indigenous nations in
canada that she works more directly
and as i'm based in brazil i work with
the international researchers
and with the indigenous researchers from
brazil and latin america so brazil peru
and mexico
yeah that's a brief introduction about
the collection so
yeah i i wonder um about what
the time of the the frame of the
coloniality
you engage in the collective because in
latin america we have a lot of
thinkers like lelia gonzalez that
engages
like a black feminist terrorist in the
the colonial movement we have also
julieta paredes who has
a more intention connected to the
indigenous communities
also some of them that talk a lot of
about echo feminism
connected to the the coloniality so what
is
the main approach to the coloniality
in the collective
yes this world is quite uh used nowadays
i guess
also in canada so the colonial studies
is sort of everywhere and applied to all
sorts of areas
and the specific way that we see
uh the coloniality from the point of
view of the gtdf collective
experiences experiments is that we see
coloniality
starting when we first started to get
separated from the land
so the separation between humans and the
land that we
step on that we live in so the earth as
not only like the earth as a system but
the earth as
the land itself where we step when we
started to detach
ourselves from that we see that process
as a start of a colonial process we
started colonizing the land
and from colonizing the land we started
colonizing one another and other human
beings
and then all the violence and systemic
and historical violence that we see
perpetuated
so i think that's a core point of view
we don't see coloniality starting
when european people came to the
americas
right it was long before that of course
that had
a huge impact as well but
it's not the case to address that
specifically
and the other thing that i think is is
very
uh core vision of the collective is also
that we
we don't see we don't see a separation
between the unsustainable ways that we
live in earth so we know that we've been
living in modern ways
that are not sustainable for the planets
that we have so if we keep going in this
direction
it's going to end soon like resources
are not enough
and this is deeply deeply connected to
the historical and systemic violence
that we see
with different people and not only like
indigenous nations but also
with people that are always um on the
bottom of the system or something like
that like in the south of the south and
so we don't see that separate we always
analyze
and we always do practices and we always
try to understand the connection between
the our
in sustainable ways ways of living and
the systemic violence
we don't we don't we do not sort of
allow in our minds the separation
um because of what i was talking in the
beginning
usually when we do the separation we are
being violent
again either with the earth or with some
some population so
we try to put that together always in a
critical way
i wonder if you could talk a little bit
more about the methods
that you guys use to engage because it's
it's like we are trapped so how do see
outside this
frame that it's kind of immersed in
every little thing we we are
so maybe the social cartographies and
the house of modernity that is the one
i'm most familiar with
it's a very good thing to talk about
yeah so we've been working with
educational experiments so both like
courses like formal courses in
universities for example when i saw
this teacher that is connected to ubc
there's another teacher
in durham in england also
so a little bit of experience
experiments happens inside the
university but most of it happens
outside of university
in an informal way so before
this situation that we are living in
we used to have like uh immersion
courses so sort of like retreats
where we would go for a week and have
these
layers of of learning together and of
uh uh together
in place right so the best way would be
to for people to go on a workshop that
they're immersed in
a lot of time and
this there was a base for this
experiments to happen that was in
slovenia in in slovenia in eastern
europe
and we used to go there like every every
summer for four years the collective has
been doing work
there with a lot of people that are
activists or working with education or
philosophy
or towards other ways of thinking and
being in the world right
uh now we are trying more and more
online versions
so we are having online courses and
study groups as well and trying to
bring this experience that was super
based on the present
to an online way and apart from slovenia
me and gino my partner we have started
here in brazil
a project called tehadentro where we
work here
a lot with brazilian people both
indigenous and non-indigenous
trying to understand where when is it
that is uh suitable for us to be working
together and when we did
that that we are doing like some work
with white people
uh mainly because it's a very different
work to be done
so yeah in these pedagogical experiments
either offline
or online now we work a lot with social
cartographies
i don't know if everyone is familiar
with but
one easy way to to explain is to compare
it with
theories theories are more like a fixed
way
of knowing that you got to that theory
and then you are going to
work from that social cartographies are
just like coming to a very simple point
would be like
drawings of a system that we understand
and then we can open a conversation from
that social cartography so social
cartography
is easier and playful and it just moves
the knowledge
it doesn't fix the knowledge so we
understand knowledge as something that
is
that should move us towards something
and then we talk a lot also uh about
what is the direction that we want to
move right with this
uh knowledge that is not fixed so where
are we going
so instead of moving forward forward
like to the front
as modernity usually brings us to think
that
is the best way right let's go forward
let's go further
we try to take take things deeper
so we try to to understand the relation
with direction in a different way and by
breaking that
in our minds by understanding that it's
not moving forward it's not a resolution
it's not solution oriented
it's not a final answer it's not only
one truth and all of that
that is really a base of the modernity
uh we try to go deeper and to understand
what are the spirals that can bring us
deeper
so work is done with a lot of discussion
of course
we put out social cartography for
example house of modernity
and then we can have a talk also
actually if we have the time
this is this is one of the cartographers
we would like to
to share a little bit with you and also
we work with other ways of exercising
our body in the space and to relate our
bodies to nature
to understand ourselves more connected
to the whole
metabolism that we are inserted in so to
bring back
those connections that we have
in ourselves and that we are connected
to a larger systems
but a lot of times we are not used to
read that so we don't have the language
to have this this relation anymore we
don't have the language that
intermediates these relations
so we try to playfully with art
sometimes sometimes with indigenous
practices sometimes
yeah just experimenting with the earth
to try
to get those connections back
maybe you could share a little bit
more about the house of modernity
because i really think it's
it's good maybe i don't know if you guys
are familiar with the this frame because
for me it really gives a
a view that is different and the sensing
of the what you're talking about
so maybe what do you guys think to share
about
the house of modernity cool not cool
let me see if i find a quick link here
so everyone can just
um maybe open
to see the drawing
just a second
um
maybe gino can you help me
i'm asking someone that is here okay i
will start talking and
then if if i find the link i will put it
out on the
chat but the house of modernity
the idea is to understand that
we have a modernity has built
one big big house on the top of the
earth
so we live in this big house that the
earth cannot
sustain anymore so what we try to do
usually is to include people inside the
house so we're like oh here in this
house of modernity is so comfortable
we have everything we have access we
have technology we have like health
and research and we have what we need
and we use the resources
but the problem is that not everyone
fits sort of
on the house i think gino sent
the the link there so if people want to
to have a look at the house or should i
share here on the screen
yeah i can give you um i can share it on
my screen or i can give you
co-host access to share maybe if you if
you want to share it's
just this the figure on this link here
thank you
well anyway so the house that modernity
built
thank you perfect the idea is so this
this house is very big for the planet
right
there are hidden costs on it so so the
the relations between on how this house
works there are costs that are not
usually
um seen by everyone so both like
waste disposal and pollution and this
kind of thing
but also expropriation and violence and
systemic
systemic violence that are perpetuated
for us
in a way to live in this comfort zone
that we live if we are here sitting in
front of each other on the internet we
are already
in some kind of a better place of this
house right a lot of people
cannot be here uh and then one
one of the the drawings that i think
it's very interesting it's the third one
on the first lane um
that is talking about the for the false
idea
the false promise of social mobility
of a universal middle class so we think
we are like we are made or we are
taught to to understand that if we
deserve
if we do well in our lives and if we can
we should do hard work
we're going to climb up those stairs
right we're going to be in a better
place
than other generations were so
it sort of depends on the individual to
make its path towards success or
something it depends on your
autonomy or your ambition and things
like that
so we are led to think that there is
this
possibility of social mobility for
everyone and
indeed there are stairs inside the house
we can see that happening we can prove
that
but the thing is that not everyone fits
in the house so a lot of people
the system is designed for a lot of
people to be on the bottom there's no
way that
everyone would go to the top of the
house or to the top of the economic
system
and because the ceiling has a limit as
you see there
not everyone fits there the system
doesn't work if everyone is in the
system is in the ceiling
and we have to remember also that
there's always a lot of people
outside of the house so when we think of
modernity as a way of living
and modern habits and modern access to
food medicines uh and other things that
are beneficial
not everyone is living this so we sort
of leaving this trans-historical moment
where history is not
aligned for everyone so this already
breaks
the the view of of modernity itself
the things that usually see things as
linear right
and things as a common a common thread
that unites us all and the thing is that
time doesn't work
in this linear way there are a lot of
people living still
nowadays as they used to live a long
time ago
and also that's where we get a lot of
learnings and teachings from and
still in this third house um there's
this division between north and south
that is related to the global north and
global south
of course there's it's not a coincidence
that
usually it's it's connected to the
geographical
division of north and south uh north of
the planet
is a lot more rich than the south of the
planet
but here we bring in uh another
ingredients that is saying that in the
north there's the south of the north
so there are in the north of the planet
people that are excluded and that are
not gaining these benefits of the modern
way
of living right so the people that are
being
systematically violated and exterminated
and still dying for the their lands and
things like that we know that this
exists also on the north
and also on the other hand the truth
also applies there's the south there's
the north of the south
so even in the geographical south
there's a lot of a lot of rich
uh rich people and like a lot of very
privileged
classes and groups of people that are
living
mostly like most of the people in the
north so that's not a linear
relation but it's important to
understand that
and most importantly to understand that
there will always be
people outside of this house so
inclusion
and just trying to repair damages that
have been done
historically usually what we are seeing
is
is that this doesn't work so we see a
structured
structural damage happening in this
house so the walls are all
broken so we see economical crisis we
see climate crisis
we see people moving for being forced to
move from one place to the other so
conflicts and uh forced migration and
all of that
that's a big big damage in this house
that modernity
built and then we are set with the
question like what should we do then
are we gonna fix all these walls are we
gonna try to
extend the house even more but then the
planet doesn't
doesn't fit this house or should we
build other types of house
how else can we live what's the other
ways of living
and that's where we come and that's
usually where we start
and to get deep in our courses and our
workshops
so what are the other ways of living and
being that we can
try to move towards because we are super
limited by the ways of thinking of
modernity
so every time that we are thinking that
we are outside of the box we are
probably just in another box right
we go to this other box and then oh now
i'm outside of the box now i'm thinking
a very different thing
but the consciousness that we try to
bring here
is that we are super trapped like deeply
in neurology bio neurologically even
attached to the strings of modernity so
what are the ways that we can do some
movements
towards other futures and that's why
also the
name of the collective it's not that we
are going to get there we're not going
to be you know the colonial future in
a couple of years or in a generation
it's an intergenerational work
it's a work that it should start and
at some point it will get somewhere we
are not sure
where is it where is it but we are sure
that we cannot be
like stuck in the situation that we are
now that is not
working for most of the people and not
working for the planet either
there was a brief scene of the modern
house
cool so there are already some
uh question here um
but maybe i can make a
small question that before the
the question and answer part that is
together
with this the practices of the social
cartographies
you have a lot of artistic experiments
that you engage
in in the collective so recently i
engaged with one created by danny
d'emilia who is one of the researchers
in the collective
who was about the name was the face
yourself
where we we had like our photos our
pictures
and we had to make a cut in our face
and we have to spend a week taking
photos of
other things in our face so it was a
kind of art therapies
experiment that for me personally it was
a very
interesting experiment and it's
it's for me it was very interesting how
in in this the face experiment we start
engaging in like liking
the ways we are putting we we engage in
other kinds of
um like other boxes that is to be liking
the photos you take with the experiments
so you know
it's for me similar to what you were
talking about when we are trying to
to even create these exercises we are so
trapped
in the frames of modernity that we want
to you know post the
the photo that we create so there are a
lot of you know layers of the straps
so my question is about what are the
other experiments
and how is this a relation with this
artistic
experiments and actually like i know
that you
has been working with art and with
museums and um in for many years in your
life so
what is also your perspective in
the like art you know what we call art
in this the colonial movement and
and also in the artistic experiment in
the collective
yes thank you yeah in the
together with the collective we have a
lot of artists working with us
and i'm very glad for that because i'm
not one of them
and and we learn a lot from what they
can bring
so i've always believed in art as a way
of changing the word for instance like
in
last sense but mainly for like taking
us out of out of the zone that we are
usually comfortable
in so out of our current most
common kind of thought so yeah i've been
working with museums and education
in museums and understanding how art can
play a role
in the shift of paradigm and
i'm more and more convinced that big
institutions are not
the way to do that though i'm still
related to some work in museums which i
love but
i don't think they can as a big
institution
make deep changes so they can like scale
things up
but they don't go very deep so i'm
much more interested now in these
pedagogical experiments that are
connected
also in using artistic experiments
inside these practices even though
sometimes it's for a group of 10 people
or
24 people and stuff like that it's in a
much much smaller scale because it has
to be experimental and you have to put
your
body there and even if it's online it it
demands
a lot of like energy coming together
but yeah i think it makes more sense now
not to
to scale it up and with artistic
experiments
what i think one that maria mentioned
uh from the artist danny demilia
for example they help us move out
of our traditional way of seeing
ourselves and seeing ourselves
as a coherent self as oneself that we
have to defend and that we have to be
or for example right uh try to be more
um to understand
i was also trying to relate with the
question here because
usually we see ourselves as very duo as
well like either we are doing something
good or we are doing something bad
are we in the right path or are we still
in the wrong path
and this kind of thing so the exercises
with art helped me
personally in my journey in the
collective as a
learn as a as a learning experience also
for me
to detach myself from this fix itself
and difficulty in myself helped me helps
me
understand how i can understand
knowledge
as a moving thing not as a fixed thing
and then maybe i'm playing with the
lines that are limiting us
with modernity um
i've been let me just say something
because we've been
talking about like some critics some
strong criticism about modernity
right and i just like to
to make sure we are sort of on the same
page
we understand that modernity has a lot
of
beneficial things that it brought to us
and we don't want to neglect that
and go back old ways to some kind of
previous ways of living and relating
so it's not about that it's about
recognizing everything that modernity
has
brought to us and understanding also
how it has been limiting ourselves to
expand
to a better in a more possible way of
living futures
so acknowledging the contradictions in
that and
embracing uh what we can
that is that is good until a certain
kind of limit
and usually the limit would be what is
good and does not affect
violently and systemically
some other people or the earth
cool so maybe
we can move to the questions we have
already three
super interesting questions one that you
already started
responding somehow so rain
should do they meant do they said right
do you want to talk yeah thanks
um thanks so much for being here
and i really liked the thing about
social cartographies
um and like knowledge that moves
um instead of being fixed um but i'm
i'm gonna shift my questions slightly
because you kind of answered
that dualism um we we deal with the
culture war
a lot on the stoa so i want to ask how
do you differentiate yourself
from some of the social justice work
that
has become kind of dumb dumbed down
um like very ideological and dogmatic
and
sort of like taking these really
important values
and uh alienating a lot of people
because of the
kind of simplicity of their arguments
and lack of ability to engage in
discourse
how do you differentiate yourself from
those
um those kind of unsophisticated
types of activism
yes very very good question and
reflection for us
to do together because
a lot of times what happens is that we
try to explain what we're doing and a
lot of people say wow i'm doing the same
thing
and my project is this one and we're
like that's
really in a different direction right so
one way that we've been trying to
to not to differentiate ourselves but to
to help everyone to have their own sort
of tools
to understand differences between
directions
so we put we sort of like set things in
a system
that is through directions and not
through fixed like tags this this
project is this and these people are
doing that
so it's not fixed attacks it's more like
where are they moving towards
so apart from the word that they are
using that sometimes is the same word
that i'm using and someone the academy
is using
what is the direction that this is
moving so we are trying to develop a
work
that are called that is called the
raiders uh
so we have now about like 12 raiders
uh that we are working on and we always
work these on
in courses and with other people so we
can
always enrich and make this process
better
it's still not very around work
but the idea is that everyone should
have the tools of raiders
to understand what is the direction that
things are going so am i moving
am i moving deep am i going deeper in
this question or am i just trying to get
to a solution
this is like one one of the main kinds
of raiders
am i moving forward am i getting just
big and
going to a resolution to a final answer
or
am i moving towards something that is
unknown
that is dark that is like
with no that i have no knowledge exactly
about it
but i feel and sense that the direction
is deeper
and one other thing very important
on how we understand direction
is that we are centering we try to or we
wonder we understand that is better
to center the earth so what is the
center of this direction is this
defending
one group of people is this defending
the woman is this defending uh
these people here that is that are
trapped and that need their land back or
is this defending the earth
as a bigger metabolism that encompasses
the woman and this group of people and
stuff like that
so we try to
to move towards the centering of the
earth
as opposed to being in one single fight
with one single
sort of discourse i do understand the
importance of single fights a lot of
times you have you are on the front line
you are trying to stop something to
happen and
you are doing one single fight and i do
respect that it's just not the space
that i work on
maybe camilla this is also connected to
the
outer intensity how do you say that in
english
maybe this is also something interesting
to
talk about yeah it took up the high
intensity and low intensity struggle
it's a
it's an important um cartography also
that we
work with is to differentiate um
who is in a high intensity struggle than
people that are in a low intensity
struggle
so this is always one one first thing
before
evaluating uh like a project or
trying to analyze what other people are
doing
we try to understand if they are in a
struggle
that their lives depend on
so people that needs to fight every day
to breathe just to have the right of
living
just to be in the land that they are and
i know canada
canada has a big
conflict and history also and
present with a lot of indigenous people
there so maybe
from that sense you can you can relate
to what i'm saying
and the difference between those and
people that are in a low intensity
struggle like
i struggle with being in this world that
is so full of problems and i'm trying to
do my work here and all of that
but i don't i'm not obliged to every day
wake up and fight if i if i
if i decide to go and work as a waitress
for a year i have this option
so if you have an option you were in a
low intensity struggle fight
and that's a very very different place
then who doesn't have this option
both because their heart is in
in a place that they cannot move out
from that
but usually i'm talking more objectively
about people that don't have this option
because their life are at risk at all
times
so that's also a way of uh sort of
calibrating our radars when we see other
work happening
um there is also done that
made some questions and so maybe you
want to speak
yes i want to hear you more people
yeah let me see if i can find my
question here
um uh
yes you mentioned earlier camille that
um
that as big institutions can
scale as you recognize that big
institutions can scale
but they may not necessarily change very
effectively
has the collective explored how to
create and build
new institutions from scratch
if so what has been your experience
thanks yeah no we haven't
we haven't worked with creating
institutions
we are still trying to work on like
margins and very
small scale projects some of us
like individually go back to
institutions and sort of
feedback that into the work that they do
in institutions
um there's this this teacher for example
this professor
in the uk sarah she tries to do her work
like to connect the work from gtdf back
to the university
and it's usually a lot of frustration so
yeah
starting a an institution from the
scratch could be
a way to do it differently i don't know
thank you
and there's also your other question
then about like the vector
vectors in the the raiders i think but i
maybe camilla had already replied
because when you were talking about
the raiders i think you you said that
right
yeah i think i think she sort of it was
more of a comment
you were talking about that when you
were um
i guess when you're coming to this is my
understanding correct me if i'm wrong
when you come together and you have a
conversation it's not so much about
what's the vision and where do you want
to end
up but it's i feel that i want to go in
this direction and i was just commenting
that directions have
um like a vector it has a direction but
it also has a magnitude
like maybe i just want to take one small
step in that direction as opposed to
i want to run a a marathon in that
direction
and that was yeah totally
i like like that and it relates to what
i was saying thank you
yeah i think it's very connected to what
you always say camilla of going
to deep in the earth like in the soil
metaphorically like a mycelium or like
and not forward and there's another uh
question of uh yosho maybe you wanna
join and say it or
yeah thanks um
oh are we hearing me
hi can you can you guys hear me
okay um yeah i had a couple questions
but then i just wanted to clarify
something first
you mentioned uh
well it's just in my own words you
mentioned so the degree to
up the rich demographic or population is
connected to the land
i think you initially said is like
correlated to
the potential for um
um the uh the colonial
mindset is that is that what
one of the sort of outcomes or findings
yeah there was that i can clarify later
but
so is there is there anything that
you're exploring
in the digital realm and now especially
with
the way that we're necessarily detached
from land and is there
um like it seems to me like there's
what you're referring to by the land is
also like there's like a
there's an inequality to the access to
various economic resources that
various populations can have so
um but and then
you know now that we're in this sort of
data driven age and there's
you know we're in these virtual
classrooms and
with everything with covid going on is
there anything that you're specifically
experimenting with um
in the virtual digital realm
i think nothing nothing major or nothing
very
like mind-blowing that we are
experiencing the digital realm
and i also understand that this is
happening because we are not
very well connected to people that are
doing
um like edge work on that
like people that are being most
innovative on that on those areas
where we as a collective are not
connected
to these people yet so we're sort of
doing the usual on the digital what has
been happening
different for for us is that
there was a lot of travel involved with
a lot of people from the collective
so a lot of times like someone was away
for a month and someone was with an
indigenous
group researching for two months and
the moments where we were together were
very
little and very precious throughout the
year and now that everyone
is back in their homes uh
we we're going much deeper in developing
our
own research so we are testing the
pedagogical experiences
with uh much faster because we have like
people available and people available
everywhere
so the availability changed a lot but
not i wouldn't say we we are we are
moving
somewhere very different using digital i
would
love to to do that more and
yeah i think that's it
thank you there is
one question of peter right
you want to join yes um
so something he said that caught my
attention was
kind of the how art is a spiritual
opportunity
and how kind of this collective is
utilizing art to kind of
make us aware of the being in the house
of modernity and and figuring out ways
to go beyond it
and i'm curious if you are integrating
any conversational like modalities
authentic relating modalities and
dominic barter is coming to mind with
restorative circles i know he's from
brazil as well
um because one of the things that we
talk here at the star
is like trauma accumulated trauma or
being in the trauma scene
and how that kind of prevents people
from deeply connecting
and being in right relationship and if
you can't be in right relationship with
another person then it's going to be
hard to be in right relationship with
you know the planet and everything else
that's uh deeply important
um so i wondered if there's that i
personally think there's a great
opportunity
to to have art and spiritual
conversations emerge so i'm wondering if
the collective is thinking anything
with that along those lines
yeah thank you one of the sort of
models that we were working last year
was having different
having difficult conversations without
relationships falling apart
so being able to say what needs to be
said
and without sort of taking it personal
and so without making it a fight and in
that sense
i would risk saying it sort of inspired
a little bit
in dominic's work with non-violent
communication and all of that i'm very
familiar
uh with his work but no we don't use
like specific uh methodologies or
restorative circles to do that
because also i think that we
we are addressing a lot the limitations
of the conversation
so at the same time that we think
difficult conversations has to happen
without the relationships falling apart
we understand the limits
of the word and of language and
this limitation is pointed back to us
very very directly when we are working
with indigenous people
and it's not something we can neglect
we're like okay
we cannot we cannot say everything we
cannot put everything on the paper we
cannot even draw everything
there are a lot of things that are
beyond
so there is a certain movement connected
to art and indigenous knowledge that is
saying
it's not always through dialogue through
dialogue
so there are these two two forces
at the same time in the work that we've
been doing
so understanding limits of the
significance and or the yeah
of the meaning of the of how we
understand each other in
language and how this can be more
limitating and suffocating then
possible of expanding our limits
something like that
so i see these two forces at the same
time so we try to do some
good dialogue but at the same time we're
not that's not
how we're gonna move
thank you it reminds me also
peter of the a poem that
uh that poem from the collective about
the violences that are brought sometimes
in the dialogues and
um that is written by i think uh
a group of indigenous people from canada
that maybe it's
it's very like it's something very
strong written it's that is
it has a feeling connected to it about
it
that is very good to read
so there is another question here one is
done again
asking how to be engaged in the
collective
involved and
with another one so maybe you want to
join
sure i seem to this session seems to be
making me very curious with questions
here
um yeah i i guess i was just
i i'm appreciating your approach and i'm
just wondering
you know i'm asking for myself and and
other attendees here
who may be uh sharing my um feelings
is there a way for the public or
for people that are you know in the
stowa here to get involved
some way with some of these experiments
that you're doing
well as a collective and very
organically
led by a lot of people we don't have
very formal ways that people can like
enter or join
for example my my story with the
collective i went to do a course
in slovenia as a student and right after
the course
i was like can i stay longer can i stay
researching with you guys i have another
couple of weeks and
and they were like yeah but we are on a
program connected to ubc canada so
people are like
sponsored like they were the fellows
that were sponsored to be there and i
was like okay but i'm here already
so i sort of like joined and from that
point i started working
with them so there's not an official
point of entry
there's a lot of material on the website
and
actually me and gino my partner we are
working in a lot of courses
in portuguese now so we have a new
course
starting like in a week i would love to
to have you with us but it's gonna be in
portuguese
and in september or probably until mid
october at the most
we will be releasing an online course
with the participation of vanessa
and in english and then open widely
so that's that's one way of of getting
in touch with our work deeply
but before that we can we can chat and
understand what is
that you do and understand how is it
that you could collaborate so
there's a lot of uh zoom sessions a lot
of a lot of meetings gatherings from the
collective
and quite a few times we invite people
from outside that are interested to join
we're like okay so this session seems to
be related
to what you do so maybe you can come as
a listener or maybe you can come and
and share with us what you work with so
yeah i will leave the contacts and
websites and things like that
do you know just sent the the poem that
i mentioned that is i can't hold space
for you anymore
yeah thank you dino so
i think we are getting in the end of the
session so
maybe camilla have a final words for us
no i think i spoke a lot already thank
you
everyone for listening what we
usually like more to do is
more like to put people in dialogue and
to understand how the social
cartographies can actually help us
having different different kinds of
dialogue but for this
one hour session and for the first time
meeting you
we thought this format would work better
just
as a sort of introduction to our work
we're going to put some
links to my work and to maria's work
here we're going to share our contacts
as well
and just hoping this is a uh a first
and initial stage of our contact i'd
love to know more also
about you all and i'm very i'm an
admirer of the work that peter
does with stoa so it's very nice for us
to be here as well
thank you thanks everyone
thanks uh keen and i also would like to
mention that
in episode three of our documentary
series
vanessa andrew who is the the creator of
the collective
uh is one of the characters and there is
also
one interview uh i think uh with with
vanessa in dialogue with biola komolafi
which is very interesting and related to
everything we've talked about so
and maybe you guys want to watch it we
will send you the links here
i think camila yeah i will send you my
link and
that's it thank you all
thank you maria camilla um yes we would
love to have you back in the store for
round two
i know maria is going to be hosting i'm
seeing some upcoming sessions hopefully
with bio i'm going to invite him soon to
the stoa
um yeah so if you'd like to support the
store you can go to the patreon page
and for upcoming events we have a really
exciting one tomorrow i think it's in
the morning uh
let's see no 1 30 p.m
eastern time uh praxis to collective
wisdom presence warmed out an insight
with benito roy nora bateson
and reya back uh the ladies of the stoa
uh it's gonna be a really exciting
session they don't they just have a
spontaneous dialogue with each other
there's like 150 people rcp to that so
check that on the website
should be really really cool um and yeah
thank you so much